[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
boom all right welcome to the stoa
everyone i am peter limberg the steward
of the stoa
and it still has a place for us to go
here and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge
of this moment and today uh
we have john zurzan here john is an
anarchist and primitive philosopher
and a critic on civilization itself
and he's the author of many books most
recently a people's history of
civilization
and how he came on my radar i think i
was like 17 or 18 or something
and i read this book running on
emptiness uh the pathology of
civilization
those really great series of essays um
and as you know if you're irregular to
the stoa we invite um
kind of bold thinkers original thinkers
eclectic thinkers that have distinct
views of of the world
um so uh yeah i'm very grateful for
john to be here today so how it's gonna
go um john and i are gonna have an
exchange
for uh 10 20 minutes um kind of the get
to know his world view a little bit
if you have any questions pop them in
the chat uh have a cue or question
before you
i'll call on you you'll meet yourself
you ask your question to john uh if you
don't want to be on youtube because this
will be on youtube
just um indicate on that chat and i'll
read it on your behalf
so that being said uh allow john to
unmute himself
how's it going today john
you got to unmute yourself uh
oh yeah if you press on mute
there you go sorry here we are
hi peter how you doing good good
so i thought um i start uh
with uh kind of an overview of your
thought because i think you read the the
cultural piece i sent you the medic
tribes and stuff
and one of the themes here at the stoa
is just holding
complexity and we've had a lot of
thinkers come in who have distinct views
um so i wonder if there is a john zurzan
101 that you can give it that might be a
lot to ask but
that's my first question for you
well i focused a lot on uh what happens
when a society is more and more
technological
because that's that's at the heart of
the whole civilization question and i
think we are now
pretty clearly at the point of seeing
all these crises converge and put into
question
things at a civilizational level
and i think it's you know that's the
heart of it and
uh the rest of it is is kind of details
i think all of the previous
civilizations we've seen have failed
and now there's really only one under
the sign of technology and capital
there's one integrated totality
in various cultures but really only one
world civilization now
and it's failing spectacularly in every
single
area every level every sphere
name one that isn't going south and
uh the point is well there's a lot of
points to it but i mean
fundamental i think we could say uh
civilization is a parasite that consumes
its
host and then the subsequent
versions uh seem in general
to have a bigger purchase because you
need a bigger host to consume and
finally we get to this one which is all
enveloping
and there's nothing outside of it really
there's almost nothing outside of it
there's a few indigenous holdouts or
something like that but
and uh so i mean all these various
efforts to to safeguard things to reform
things to salvage something
they're really they really mean nothing
they just
that's why so many people have thrown in
the towel they had very very weak
solutions they
looked at things at anything but they
required depth
the needed to address the problem
and they're gone i mean they're just
giving up like
you know all sorts of political types
too not just uh
say environmentalists but uh you know
lots of other
people too it's just uh game over
really that's so you've got to if you
see it
as a civilizational problem then what is
very difficult
obviously is to ask the question
civilization
yes or no it's hard to say no even if
you
uh even if and when you've decided it is
exactly the problem
that's that's what causes all this
starting with domestication
starting with that epical shift to
control
the control deepens and uh
broadens and you know it's just it's
it's a continuum that's fairly easy to
chart
i think paul shepard said it well when
he was he was sort of referring the late
anthropologist paul shepard referring to
things like nanotechnology and a lot of
a lot of current high-tech things he
said it's all there at the start
it's there in the first step it's
implicit in the first step which is a
step to domestication
to agriculture to the domination of
nature and it feeds on itself it's
it's a progression that i think is easy
to spot
uh easy to track and then you get to the
place where
the control is total and that's not just
in terms of science it's
obviously in terms of say survival
surveillance
uh you know it's it's uh
the whole name of the game is control
how do you how do you
pursue that and uh
make it stronger make it more extensive
and uh and here we are
and here we are with everything uh
really failing
and the the technology part let me just
go back to that for a second
i think that's very central in so many
ways partly because
political ideology used to have
certain answers or claims or promises
the american dream or what have you
well that's that's really it's really
worthless it's
very few people believe in that stuff
anymore so
i think the promises and claims that
technology makes
every day in all the huge ads and
everything else
have stepped into that vacuum and now
that's what is going to either help us
or heal us or create a brave new
future and i say that with some irony uh
and it's very hard to believe
but i think that's what's happening i
mean in other words it's hard to
swallow given that we have more and more
and more technology
and things are getting worse and worse
and worse for the individual for society
for the physical environment do you name
it
there we go it could go on and on but
some idea yeah yeah i want to double
click on the technology piece in a
moment but i was thinking it would be
prudent to come to terms um you had that
label anarcho primitivist
um attached to you and in your work you
have a dualism between
primitive and uh civilized where
primitive is like
you know non-alienated wild uh
non-hierarchical
while civilized is um alienated
domesticated uh hierarchical
uh so i was wondering if you can kind of
expand on that concept a little bit more
of that dualism that you have in your
work
well yeah i think you put it very well
that's uh that's i would say that's an
accurate way to put it in the thumbnail
way well it's it's the idea that
imparted to the idea that if the future
isn't somehow primitive
there won't be a future if we just keep
going down this suicidal road
uh that's that's the end of it it really
is
uh in terms of the human experience in
terms of
boy civilization sure was great wasn't
it or
or maybe it destroyed everything it was
just a path of ruin
time after time and now this time as
well
so yeah it's a i mean there are
anarchists uh
some some of us who see rewilding as the
course
and i think that goes along with the the
perspective of some
native folks who see decolonization
i think the two can be fairly linked
i think some of us are pursuing that
anyway in a more in a more real
sense uh or in a more uh
maybe down-to-earth sense decolonization
maybe is easier
to picture or or think about or proceed
with than
rewilding because rewilding after all
that means d
domestication we're all very
domesticated
i certainly am we can have these ideas
about domestication but
shedding the domestication is quite
another thing
i mean i don't know if we're ever going
to do that i don't know if we're ready
at all to do that to tackle that but uh
that's that's the way out of this it
seems to me
to refuse all these different uh
institutions and
and values that have brought us to this
uh sorry place
so the circle back to the technology
piece uh
you're critical on technology but also
on what john vicki would call
psychotechnologies like
math or the concept of time um that are
complicit in the destructiveness that
civilization brings could you
um speak more on that well in the 80s i
wrote what turned out to be a series
of i guess five essays i didn't think of
it as a series at the beginning of it or
anything but uh
what are the categories or the
dimensions
of alienation in other words where does
all this get started
and i was thinking about it in terms of
time number language
art and agriculture to
it's very speculative i mean some some
of the pieces more than others
the language one is very speculative
perhaps more
uh more so than the others but when do
you start seeing this estrangement
in other words for example let's take
the concept of number
not numbers but number itself if you can
put it that way
where did that enter human existence
where is the need
to count things to to come up with that
uh category of thinking uh number
uh well it's not too hard to see the
connection
it doesn't mean it's totally evil or uh
or horrible i
i think it's the start of that but uh
when do you need to count things you
know that's that's a certain stage of uh
society and it's it's
eminently necessary with domestication
with private property with farming and
all that you've got
you've got the commodity and
whereas before prior to domestication
how to gather life
banned society egalitarian
every anthropology 101 will tell you
that it was based on
sharing the fundamental ethos was
sharing
equality that sounds like uh made up by
anarchists
to make a point but it's not it's just
uh it's really uh
it's just a truism
and well time and here we are this
dimension that one is another example
we're totally colonized by time uh
myself included uh it stands over us
as a materiality well where did that's
where did that get started
where is the time consciousness there
are we
we tend to think that uh some societies
early well hunter-gatherer societies
didn't have a notion of time time didn't
exist
in so far as time is a consciousness of
time
and objectified uh whatever it is and
no one can quite die no one can quite
identify what that word means time
einstein said it's what a clock measures
yes but what is it that's being measured
i mean
you know he he didn't he didn't want to
get into that
because it says it's a little
complicated
but that's you know these things start
somewhere
and it it strikes me it's not a
coincidence that the development of
certain things uh
well it's not a coincidence that they
they grow uh a pace they they're
related to a situation and a situation
which is changing
and they it's a part of an adjustment to
something and
and a way to make that something grow
when it becomes the dominant order when
it becomes the uh
the ruling paradigm the ruling set of
structures and all that then it's then
it's very easy to see
you know the fact i think time is
you could say time and alienation are
the same thing
you can you can chart one just like the
other your time consciousness is a
measure of
of your estrangement your alienation
anyway that's the stuff uh yeah that i
wrote
that stuff in the 80s and
some some originality there i guess some
have said i should have quit in the 80s
because
i haven't come up with anything very new
since but uh
we're all trying to contribute trying to
contribute to this
dialogue that which has to be
transparent and honest if it is to be a
dialogue
so we'll pivot into the chats in a
moment as much questions being populated
and i think we kind of fleshed out a
good um
architecture of your views
when we were exchanging over email you
said you had some thoughts on
uh late stage civilization our current
situation
a lot of people are saying that we are
in a meta crisis or an omni crisis
um so i'm curious what is your thoughts
on what is happening now
well yeah i think that's quite accurate
to put it that way those are
those are uh words that have a certain
ring it sounds like
uh it's kind of hard to miss isn't it do
you think there's anybody out there
things are going in a good direction
fundamentally uh or otherwise i mean
it's
it's catastrophic and it seems like the
pace of it is accelerating
you know we we look at our grandkids and
i'm sure we're not the only ones that
will wonder what kind of a world will
they have in
maybe even five years i mean um
not to mention the future
uh more generally speaking and you know
all these pathologies that maybe they
speak to this
uh as loudly as anything
since the late 90s for example here in
the us
the mass shootings the school shootings
now there's church shootings mall
shootings workplace you know
there's a
it's keep it keeps getting worse and
it's even
it's even emerging more that
if the pandemic is lessening or
lightening up i don't know if it is but
you know there's been certain return to
school and work and so forth
uh which may or may not obtain it may
not keep going that way but
you come right back to the mass
shootings
you know out of nowhere and it's it's
just a remarkably
scary thing because it seems to me one
of the most
um one of the
typical responses in the story about a
shooting
is something like well the guy never
missed work he never played his music
cloud he was very polite and stuff
then he went in there and killed 20
people no history of mental illness
no criminal record just snapped
that is pretty damn telling and that
isn't
that is that's only one uh little slice
of it of course now we got rising
suicide rates
uh people are less and less healthy uh
the place is awash in the statistics
about
anxiety and depression even longevity
rates have started to stall
it used to be a bottom line answer to
some of our thinking and people would
say well yeah that all that's
interesting but
people have never lived longer we live
longer and longer
well that's not quite so true anymore
that and if you count all the people
i mean i'm not saying we don't count
them but
all the people that are totally
dependent on the medical industry
taking half a dozen uh drugs a day to
stay alive
quality life is very very poor they're
still living but
not compared to we used to be robust we
used to be healthy
and by the way speaking of longevity
people used to say well yeah but hunter
gathered in life they were all dead by
30.
well that's just not true that's a comic
book fiction
like a lot of other things about uh the
record of prehistory so anyway
yeah it's just there isn't any part of
it and it's easy to see how
interconnected or interdependent these
things are
you could just read a newspaper once a
while you could see it plainly
this is the age of pandemics it's also
the
you know whatever it's the age of mega
storms it's edge of
uh every kind of extreme extreme weather
and so forth i mean it's uh
it's getting worse and everybody knows
it
all right um so let's go to the
q a uh anjon you had uh quite yet two
questions um
the one on population uh uh the
reduction of population
could you ask that one hey john
um thanks for doing this q a um
reading um the unibomber manifesto had a
was a big turning point in my life um
growing up with technology
and having to question what the water
around me was
for the first time i had two questions i
guess i could start with my first one
the carrying capacity of a
hunter-gatherer lifestyle would be
significantly less than 7 billion people
do you think there needs to be methods
to reduce population to accomplish this
way of living
how do you suppose this may happen
well one could imagine anyway uh a
possible reversal
i mean it was domestication that started
the huge
increase in population uh it was
uh at the beginning it was in absolute
numbers it wasn't a lot but
but uh you know in a percentage it's
just gigantic just
leaped up but the only other thing
comparable is the industrial
revolution when the factory system got
going another great big spike in
population
so if you remove those basic things that
drive this
you would be going in a healthier
direction because
it isn't it isn't a natural phenomenon i
mean
uh noam chomsky is he's uh he's said to
us a few times not to our face but uh
he said look you primitivists are insane
and genocidal there's seven billion
people to feed
and uh and the question occurs to one
uh mr chomsky why are there seven
billion people
how did that happen what drove that come
on don't
don't just yeah we know how many people
there are
and we don't want anyone to starve but
it's that's the
doing nothing about it having more
development because we've got more
people
we need more development more factories
uh
more everything uh more global warming
obviously
i mean that's that's nuts that's what's
nuts that's just suicide
so i think you know it's i i'm not
saying this would be
easy to figure out what parts of a
process or a
transition would be needed to
bring down the numbers uh but
you know it's that's got to be tackled
and i think that's
you can see where it comes from so well
take away those things take away
domestication and industrialization
then we'd be on a healthy path and i
think including a healthier number of
people on this planet
you have a follow-up luncheon
um it's a slightly different question
john
um i'm trying to understand the
difference between
technique and technology um and kind of
jacqueline i'm curious if you can kind
of explain
your angle on it and kind of how it's
influenced your work i've been thinking
a lot
about the concept of molok and so i'm
curious if this distinction helps
understand that
well i gotta confess i've never
understood that distinction
and you know a little i think maybe part
of it maybe i'm just trying to get off
the hook here but
you know uh the technological society
he's writing in this uh rather abstract
french style they're trained in this
kind of classical
uh mode to to the language to writing
uh and it can be rather abstract i mean
i
i'm i've tried to figure out what what's
the difference would
this technique sound more uh
i don't know reputable or something i
don't know
but i think it's you can break it down
maybe
in fact i think you mentioned uh in
passing the unabomber manifesto
so-called manifesto peter
you know that's nothing but that's
nothing but jacqueline put into more
american or
vernacular language you don't have to
puzzle over what his technique is that
some esoteric
definition he has that we don't know or
you know that
in fact kaczynski told me that and he
said that was uh
that's kind of what it is industrial
society in its future is the
is the easy form of the technological
society
that's pretty much all it is he added a
few things but
much easier to read
cool um nick
benjamin you got a question
thank you peter hi john i'll just read
my question
um while life under late stage
capitalism tends toward
alienation stress the meaningless
accumulation of wealth
moral bankruptcy and a host of other
ills if we're honest
it remains the undisputed attractor of
desire
its libidinal pull has us all desiring
our self-desecration
though most of us remain unaware where
and how do you see us countering this
architecture of compulsion
with alternate attractors of desire that
can shift humanity toward more beautiful
futures
oh that's a good one but it strikes me
that in the 60s
we saw a little bit of lessening of that
i remember
a marxist friend mine said
the hippie thing is just a loss of
commodity fetishism
uh that's one way to put it in other
words
i don't think the uh the gravitational
pull of that
is so total as we might think
i mean it's um
of course that's just a hopeful impulse
i guess i mean we
we don't really know if people can step
outside of this
john you see you when you walk outside
you see
almost everybody from my generation at
least walking around with their heads
and their phones these
engines of compulsion that that connects
them to
libido marketplaces where they can while
away their time
spending all their money and all their
attention um
so so we're all hooked you know um yeah
yeah
i know it drives me crazy and i do some
work over at the university of oregon
or that is a haunted library is there
sometimes and you see these
kids they're just like zombies you know
they just run into you because they
can't see anything else but it's a tiny
screen
and you could project they're gonna get
up with maybe their phone is in their
hands as they sleep and they're going to
plug it in right away and
then they go to work or not everybody
does that if there are people that
actually work with their hands somewhere
but
you know and it's just a lifelong deal
but i don't know
you know the the i don't know what we
would call it maybe it's the uh
just just being so enveloped
is a is a condition that's somewhat
imposed in other words
i think there's a lot of uh well i don't
know if you'd call it evidence but i've
read a lot of stuff about how
talking to these people they're not in
love with it
they're bored with it but there's
nothing else you know we've gotten to
this stage of separation where
and it didn't happen overnight but but
that's what they're left with and i
i don't know whether it would be uh
and as you say yeah it's hooked up to
everything else
you know you can chat with your family
or you can order stuff or
whatever i mean of course that's what if
there wasn't any use value to it it
wouldn't exist but
but it but i'm not so sure that
you know people are so enamored of it i
just
otherwise i'm just just to add to that
i'm riffing off a book written by a
leotard a french philosopher called
libidinal economy
i think liberal economy where he
famously
says that the the um the worker in the
factories
in in the 19th century uh 19th century
beginning of capitalism
um rather of industrial capitalism uh
inherently desired his own
destruction um desired his own
anonymizing alienation
and uh and so it's it's actually not
it's not a question of
being enamored it's a question so it's
almost a question of masochism
of of facing this this
flow downhill towards complete and utter
moral bankruptcy
and and alienation and somehow desiring
that
i don't quite know where this goes but
i don't think it's a question of being
enamored by these by these devices but
rather
being just just completely disarmed by
them
well maybe that's typical of the gloom
and pessimism of today to come up with
an idea like that for one thing it
overlooks the
mammoth amount of struggle the mammoth
amount of resistance
to industrialization i've written a fair
amount on that topic and
uh it doesn't seem like they were just
giddily uh uh going for it or
uh wanting that wanting their life ways
to be completely put to waste by the
machine
chapters in my book a people's history
of civilization
testifies to that i think or or the
classic
work of a giant classic as probably no
uh
the making of the english working class
uh that's that's a that's just full of
that
is for example the famous hand bloom
weaver is in england
uh often would rather starve than go
into the factories
i mean they were just uh there were
means there were pressures there were
realities that
to conquer these people and it took
decades to do it and
it was a bloody struggle just like it
was
to achieve domestication you know people
have said
well if it was such a horrible thing why
did people take it
pick it up and go for it you know why
did they jump into farming
well it wasn't uh it wasn't exactly a
free choice
there were there was so much resistance
to it i mean it's
that's the that's the real story you
know the cliche
the victors write the history well
that's
yeah that's so that's kind of uh you
know it's overlooked quite a lot because
they lost
so it doesn't mean they didn't fight
back
all right um we're going to go to rachel
haywire's question next on the art
because i thought that would be a good
one to
pick you back off hi
how are you hi there i
am curious about art and how you view
the primal expression related to our
in conjunction with civilization has
already been colonized
have we lost our ability to primarily
express ourselves creatively or is there
some type of
hope or like renaissance possible
well i hope there is with art just like
i hope there is with writing i'm a
writer so uh
but you know i've looked at this largely
in terms of the uh what is called the
sapient
paradox i just ran across this although
what what this refers to i've been
i've been thinking about for decades
really and that is the question of
the how why is symbolic culture so
recent it's practically just like
seconds ago in terms of the whole sweep
of
the two million years of homo species
uh there was no art and about 35
000 years ago which is you know blink of
an eye really relatively
then we get to kmart we got the
artifacts of of
symbolic uh culture which
a little bit before it became a culture
but there was there was the symbolic you
could see it in the uh
not just the cave art but anyway at the
same time we know that
people were able to do
amazing uh things what we would call
behaviorally human
capacities skills over a million years
ago
easily over a million years ago so it
wasn't that they weren't bright enough
to come up with art
but somehow they didn't i mean it's so
um so i've actually tended to see this
as a kind of a
compensation uh you you get art but
you've got to give up a lot to then
have that dimension to have that the
satisfaction of art
but it may be a trade-off there and uh
along the lines somehow you've we've
we've tended
to lose the immediacy and so many other
things about uh pre-domesticated life
that maybe you didn't need art just like
it didn't need number
or you know these other things i mean
people seem to be doing fine i mean i
will never know what their consciousness
was how they were feeling about it or
i mean you know it's kind of an
implication that they were just totally
happy to not have art but
well we don't know that but you know
what i mean there there were
there were things that were missing uh
and they were largely the bad things
that were missing so you can
kind of make some conjectures about how
um you know people went along with
with with without complex society
without domination of nature
without hierarchy and all this other
stuff so uh
and you know the archaeologists have
always puzzled over this
i'm not the only one you know well why
were they so stuck they didn't change
anything they didn't improve anything
they weren't
inventing the future or nothing but and
i don't know it just sometimes they just
get back to the cliche
if it ain't broke don't fix it
you know if it's fine then why jump off
into something else
which quickly becomes not fine anyway
that's just part of the
you know conjecture about it
any follow-up question uh rachel
yeah it's interesting that you put it
like that
as art being just a another invention
because
i feel like a lot of artists have been
trying to bring back this primitivism
through art you know like as a vehicle
to have a re-experiencing of the times
that we
have lost to civilization and kind of
like this colonization of the force of
life i mean i see art as um
like one of the few fields where people
still do have um
more of that primal energy um you know
like just in terms
of of primal expression right um like
the
the primal inner you know
primitive soul in in the human right um
and i guess my question is um even
though it already is a modern
invention that probably doesn't need to
exist for people to thrive
um is it possible within the modern
context for art to leave uh
a primitive mark that could beckon
people positively
uh-huh uh-huh yeah that's that's a good
question
we're we're grappling with what we have
you know with language with art with
you know trying to add something to the
equation
and maybe find a way out of this
so uh yeah
music i mean these these these areas uh
that's that's where we're at and we're
trying to do something with what we have
i haven't given up writing because i've
raised some
uh questions about language
you know so it's in fact i have a
somewhat
infamous essay called uh the case
against art
and it's not it isn't the case against
art i was just you know being
provocative with the
title but it's more about origins of art
anyway let's yeah that's a good question
i think you raised
cool thank you rachel uh our resident uh
primitive artist um evan you had a
question
hi yeah let me pull up the what i
actually wrote um
so my my question here is um
about the sort of concept of of the
extended phenotype um
so you know uh beavers build dams uh
wasps spilled nests um lots of animals
create things that aren't just their
physical bodies
um as part of their nature and when we
talk about um the sort of primitivism or
the
sort of return to these more
hunter-gatherer or nomadic
pre-agricultural pre-domestication
societies
um every one of those that i'm aware
that we have records of still
developed something that we would
consider technology i mean
bows and arrows spears flint napping etc
and and so it seems like the seeds of
technology are
in humanity itself and so i wonder
let's suppose that we were able to get
rid of domestication and agriculture
what are your thoughts about how we
would prevent the whole cycle from
happening again
or is it desirable i assume it's
desirable to prevent the whole cycle
from happening again but
but what are your thoughts on that
basically
well to me it's it's instructive to make
the distinction between
tools and technology tools
uh especially tools that don't require a
division of labor or
specialization because when you get into
uh when you get into the division of
labor then
then you have systems of technology
pretty early on
whereas if you have whereas a tool
you know you can see you can see the
values there or the potential values
anyway there
there there's an intimacy there's a
flexibility
there's an equality in terms of again
simple tools
and those you don't have those things
uh you have them less and less as as
things develop
and you have the complexity
of technology so i think
you could say that everything is a
technology but
it's it's it's possible to to be more
exact about the uh
definitions i think and that's where
yeah the equality comes in if if for
example if everybody's able to do
roughly the same stuff
then one person isn't installed at a
higher
level or some effective level of control
over anyone else
because you know that's not needed you
can
for example tools there's you know
there's some scholarship about that
there's no gender
difference women or men
could make stone tools or you know it's
you don't have these incipient uh
gradations
of power or authority that or the shaman
i mean it's possible that the shaman was
the first specialist
and the shaman is not exactly a horrible
figure although
there are certainly in the literature
you can find
instances where the shaman is is really
a cop
it really uh wields his power over
others
and used it not necessarily in a
wonderful spiritual way because it was
there
because the authority was there and
maybe
before it was a generalized condition
people knew
what that shaman knew but it ends up in
the in the hands of
fewer people and then you then you have
a potential problem
do you have a follow-up question or
comment evan
um yeah so i great answer um so i see
the distinction you're pointing to
between tools and technologies so my
my within that frame my follow-up
question would be something along the
lines of
what are your suspicions about what
caused the shift in some cultures
all cultures have tools and it seems
that only some cultures developed
technology and the since you're speaking
of agriculture
systems of domination specialization etc
what do you think is the key
differentiating factor between the
cultures that natively did and the
cultures that natively didn't
wow that's a that's a huge one and i'm
i'm sure
i'm sure you would agree it varies from
place to place and uh
climactic and other factors uh but uh
you know that's that's one of these
questions i i just don't know the answer
i mean you
uh like people have pointed out in in
germany in the 30s there was a little
town or a village
it was all pro hitler pro-nazi and a
couple of
kilometers away one that was not
and they seem to be the same there's no
big difference
that's noticeable in terms of the
political choice
so i don't know i i just you kind of
wonder what is it that
uh that force either forces people or
draws people to
do something different i mean it's not
always
it isn't perhaps strictly i mean some
people think
it's the question of population you've
got
more miles to feed so then you've got to
start farming because that's a more
reliable or possibly a more reliable
means of feeding people and then the
other point of view is
which is more mine that the population
didn't start increasing until
domestication set in
you know so you're kind of you're kind
of putting the cart before the horse
but i think that's uh i think that's a
difficult uh
perhaps even existential question to
some degree as to why
it made easier progress in some places
and others
just really did resist
all right uh carlos uh you're up next
i don't think we can hear you carlos
[Music]
see you uh okay can you hear me now yeah
you're good
yeah sorry i've been having some
microphone issues uh hi john i
hope your uh air quality is doing all
right out there
um we got way less smoke in this past
several days thanks
uh so my question is uh in
how to change the course of human
history by graber and
wenger the author the authors present
research that suggests
uh at some point in history humans were
flexible in terms of their social
structures
switching between hunter-gatherer
lifestyles
and cities uh do you think this sort of
model would be a sort of transitional
phase and re-wildly
well i think there's got to be
flexibility there's got to be openness
where
it isn't so easy to to ponder these
things or maybe it is i mean i don't
know you
think maybe it is easier to see
alternatives
when what uh obtains
isn't working you know but
you know and i think historically it
doesn't really work out that way people
become
often more conservative when things are
rough
for example the us in the 30s that
wasn't a very radical period
actually and so many people thought it
was the end of capitalism but they still
didn't
you know didn't do a whole
bunch of radical things that we might
have thought they would under those
circumstances you know i have to say
and it's a sad thing that graber died
last week at only 59
but he was trying i think this is fair
to say
he was trying to avoid the question of
domestication
he was trying to look at it differently
and put something else in its place
and he was he was trying to find places
for example in prehistory that
that did have some domestication but
were
uh not so bad you know didn't have all
the evils
and i'm not saying they can't be found
there's always exceptions to any rule
i think but uh but i mean that was his
he was pretty set on that and i guess
his friend wengrow
as well they didn't want to they didn't
want to agree with the primitivists
to put you know put it kind of uh
bluntly i guess
and uh there was a little bit of
hostility on that front
which doesn't mean one is right and what
is wrong but
uh you i think you have to read it as an
effort to
it's the problem isn't really
domestication
and i don't think that's very sound i
mean i don't think that's
uh i don't know why he's trying to avoid
that
but i bet again i think that uh if we're
not
able to uh you know to
address these things to try to openly
cope with what we're facing then
yeah we gotta have that and i don't know
where it comes from i mean it's
i see some hopeful signs but you know
but it's a damn
picture at the same time you know we
think we all know that
it's bleak for anarchists or anybody
else
all right um scott
you're up thanks peter uh
john um just want to thank you for your
work i was influenced by you
20 years ago when my kids were uh very
very young and
um i was following a kind of a
hunter-gatherer
influenced uh parenting style based on
the continuum concept and
and and i encountered her work and it
was very resonant
um particularly in terms of like
understanding the mindset difference to
to nurture
and then i try to to learn more about
you i was completely
new to primitivism or it didn't really
know much about it but i found an
article about you
um stating that you were
a that you were living uh
with someone and taking care of their
children and i thought that was very
interesting
that and i met i imagined that
if i somehow needed a nanny i would want
you to be
my kid's nanny wow
so i was just wondering if you could
comment on that experience of
of being a nurturer of very young
children and being in that position of
to domesticate or not to domesticate and
and what insights you got from that
experience
well the parents man it's it's
i think it's a lot easier to write about
these things than to enact them
yeah in the 80s i sort of threw a couple
of friends that could no longer
do that i kind of came into that
temporarily and ended up
80s and 90s i guess uh doing a lot of
that really enjoying it
and also my time that if i could have
had this uh at the east blair housing
co-op in eugene
where i was there for uh john
i'm just gonna jump in your i don't know
if you're touching your mic but it keeps
going in and out and we hear some
friction
oh sorry keep my hands off the thing
thanks yeah that was a somewhat similar
experience
and uh i learned a lot i was living
across the street
in uh a joint household
this was in the 80s late 80s and uh
and an artist friend of mine said well
you want to apply to the co-op you know
and i i
lived across the street but i didn't
even know it was a co-op anyway
uh i learned an awful lot of that and
there were a lot of single parents
that co-op was oh 40 50 adults
and then children a lot of single
parents
uh single dads as well as single moms
and i
anyway things it was a self-managed
thing it went you know committees
deciding stuff and people doing the work
the upkeep and so on
and i one thing i discovered is how
and maybe i sort of knew this
intellectually maybe but
i didn't really know it i mean the
difference between the way women operate
the way men tend to operate was really
instructive i mean it was just
it just seemed to me in the other
exceptions and everything but just a
healthier
let's get this done rather than kind of
jockeying for
influence or you know competing with
other guys or something it was uh
it was pretty noticeable and uh
yeah that they uh the time with uh
taking care of kids
i had no money and that so it's a
wonderful thing just on that level but
more than that it was it was great
all right um so this might be the last
question or we might have one more
uh after it uh pde uh if you can
interact um sir i'm
just maybe as a natural bias tempted to
take the
the optimist position on civilization
um and the optimist story it
has to be some version of well look yes
civilization
has like these really profound sources
of unsustainability
you know a population globally climate
change
um maybe some questions about what we're
doing with digital technology
things certainly can't go on in their
present form
um but you can also see like fairly
like these are really new problems and
you can see some fairly
large and impressive efforts um
within the kind of weird systems that we
have to try to tackle them you know
global capitalism for all like its late
stage problems
is trying to get carbon under control um
technologists are trying to figure out
how to make digital technology that
isn't terrible we're like we haven't
figured it out yet
um and so with that optimistic take
and then the primitivist take i guess
the question that i'm drawn to is like
how do
what kind of methodology can we use to
decide between these perspectives do you
have a
like a a way you like to
to argue this out systematically with
with those of us who
who either say yeah we'll probably get
through this or
there's no other way but to get through
it right it's like civilization has to
go
through or not back well i guess
i guess one starts empirically i mean uh
are these things turning out
are they is uh is it a fruitful
record of progress with these things and
i don't know where you can find uh that
it's all working out just a little more
technology and that's gonna be always
here
and yet uh the record uh not so sure
it's showing that
it's it seems to me it's deeper
deepening the problem and
you know i mean we all want some relief
we all want uh things to work and uh not
be
uh so uh scary or
making us more vulnerable but
and part of it or maybe a large part of
it is
i mean you keep reading about ais
marching forward and self-driving cars
and
everything else and uh maybe they'll
maybe they will work out the kinks to a
lot of that but
you know i think the bottom line is
health
and it just seems to me it is a sorry
damn picture
i mean i know i have friends that
are totally relying on drugs to get
through the day i have a very suicidal
friend
uh this is somewhat new you know the
severity of it is new and it's just
people are just they're not in good
health it's
the dis-ease of it all isn't just it's
not just to play on words but
the disease has to do with dis-ease and
it's not
there's something wrong with it there's
something
that really doesn't satisfy maybe
can't satisfy on the level of technology
even though well and of course there's
every different shade or
gradient of of optimism and
i'm glad somebody to bring up to bring
up the other point of view
but um i mean for example the
transhumanists they're just giddy we'll
get to the singularity
there'll be so much technology we'll
reach the
well the singularity and it's suddenly
bang everything will be fine
we'll live forever everything will be
healed meanwhile
uh more and more of it as i said
uh doesn't seem to be easing anything it
just really doesn't i see
i was quoting on my weekly radio show
the other night uh
citrix and i never even heard of citrix
i guess it's some giant
networking uh outfit some high-tech
outfit
and they had a long full-page ad and
part of it read
imagine what we could be if technology
pulled out
all the stops and i was just staggered
by that
it isn't pulling out all the stops for
one thing
and be all we can be i mean people are
in sorry shape man it's just
i can't believe how this walking wounded
man
there's and of course there's tons and
tons of written on that and
you know you could say well these are
the people that are what are they losers
or what are they
they got a point to make a point to make
or some
well now the overwhelming weight of it
from academia as well as from
journalists and the whole
the whole thing there is no disputing
the picture
and i just don't think more and more of
this is going to
is going to be the solution
do you have a quick follow-up pde
you're mute
i don't think i do i mean i feel it
feels like a reasonable answer and
you know to to to then to try to get
into the weeds on each of those
directions you know other mitigations
for climate change working
like yes to some degree possibly way too
slowly
um mental health
uh i i don't feel like i know that the
numbers
well enough clearly you could make a
case that there are like psychologically
unhealthy things about
contemporary western societies um
uh and maybe that turns out to be true
though it probably doesn't cause
fundamental unsustainability it's like
something that's bad about them
um that we should try to fix and then
population
i think people have you know for 30 or
40 years have been saying oh it seems to
be fine
and i'm really not sure that it's fine
um
but uh that one looks like the big
unaddressed crisis that that
pro-civilizationists and primitivists
will have to grapple with together
yeah yeah yeah this
is a lot of moving parts and uh
you know i look for the upside i look
for the silver lining and
i i feel personally fine you know but
that doesn't mean anything it doesn't
mean i'm unaware of
the what i would call the growing
immigration
uh and not just psychologically but uh
but yeah we have to grapple with all
this somehow and
i'm just hoping that there's more ways
to
uh open up the dialogue you know to have
more of a conversation
that includes more you know that's
that's allowed that's
uh that can be seen as as permissible or
respectable and uh i hope so before too
much
more time is allowed to go by
all right um so we're coming
to the close uh so
uh john any closing thoughts for us
anything you'd like to leave us with
oh boy um
i know all these questions were coming
at you from all these different
directions but
that's sort of the what happens at the
stoa oh yeah
no it's great to have this uh be able to
have this conversation it's terrific
we just have to strive to get more of it
and
and i do think there there are some
they're not enough i was expecting
more that there would be by this time
more of an opening
to be raising questions like these and
uh
i don't know if it's just happening a
little bit but uh
you know i don't want to be painting
some over optimistic picture either
we'll
just see uh now of course here in the
states that
the dominant media the corporate media
is about a hundred percent
all about the presidential election
and and of course rightly so about the
pandemic
but it's there's even less room at the
moment
to kind of step back and and
you know trying to look at things more
basically
um you know i mean
because the whole thing is really i mean
for example voting i mean that's
like we all know i think everybody here
would agree i'm guessing here but
uh trump is absolutely loathsome just a
you know a despicable individual
and so people say well you got to vote
you got to vote it's it's between life
and death
well it isn't it's between death and
death to pick the other guy
it keeps on getting worse it's not going
to save anything
i mean he's as a person i'm sure he's
more decent than trump for god's sake
but so what i mean
you know that's you're letting it slip
by it's just
that's not going to work anyway that's
sorry to get off under that
cool so uh in a moment i'll make some uh
announcements but uh
john thanks so much for coming to the
stoa we'd love to have you back
um appreciate it thank you so we we do
have an event uh
coming up in a half hour which you might
be interested in john
uh it's called uh how to be an anarchist
uh
my boy glenn wallace is going to speak
and glenn i think is in the audience
right now
uh glenn if you want to meet yourself
and kind of
plug what's coming up hi everybody
thanks so much i was a pleasure to
listen to john
anyone interested in contemporary
anarchism can't help but
come across his work and bump into his
name all the time uh
real pleasure um yeah i'm going to talk
about anarchism
from quite another a different
perspective
uh what john take took today anyway this
kind of wide sweeping large view of
things
uh i'm going to talk in terms of how we
might actually start employing
certain anecdotes values and strategies
uh in our lives
and i would love to have a conversation
with with you and i i would i would love
to
get some of those questions and comments
that john got and discuss them a little
more
uh for about a question about desire i
think is a fascinating important
question a question about
art and so forth so i hope i hope some
of you
joined us at eight thank you beautiful
thank you glenn and then the link to
rsvp to that directly is above i post in
the chat
uh we have tons of events coming up the
stowaway you can check it out the
store.ca
um your boy chomsky is coming in uh john
in november um so feel free to come to
that one
and if you like to support us on patreon
while we steal the culture you can do
that
by clicking um a link there that being
said everyone hope to see you in a half
hour
and thank you again for coming to stowa